Alright then gang in the last video we were talking about variables and with the
different type data types that come in that come along in the Java programming
language and as I said like the language itself data types in Java are also
platform independent and now for example if you were requirements such as this is
a double variable and you want it to be or let's say we had this int variable
that is second var and we want to save this int to a variable of a different
type and that is for example if I want to say something like this I'll say
shot s to second var and you'll notice that the compiler immediately gives you
an error it's unhappy and the reason is because these are of different data
types and second var is of a data type that is int which has 4 bytes in which
takes 4 bytes in memory and then shot just takes 2 bytes in memory so a bigger
data type variable cannot be put into a smaller data type variable right and
that is because if but if you would have done this same thing in C or C plus
plus this would have worked because the value would have been truncated and
and you would just get the equivalent value which would be in a shot but
not not in Java because Java is very strict with types and what happens is
here you can get away with this we have a workaround and that is called explicit
typecasting or in shot we call it typecasting so what we can do is we can
just put this shot in a pair of circular braces and you see that the error
immediately goes away and now what happens is we're signaling to the compiler
that second var is of type in please convert it into shot first and then save it
in a variable of type shot and this way you're just saving a variable of type
shot in a value for type shot in a variable of a type shot and that's why it
works or for example for that fact if this was of type double C again you would
have got an error not unless you do something like this and this time I'll do a
setup right so now sorry this time I'll again do a shot so what we are saying is
this F has to be converted into a shot and then put in a variable of type
shot and this should work I'll just put in a sound again and I'll just say
value now in S is and calculate it with the variable S and let's go on and
run this quickly and see it for ourselves and it just gives you see it first the
value of F was 78.9 when it was a variable of type double but now it has been
converted into shot and you saw after the point after the precision the
decimal everything goes away and then you just get a 78 so the compiler is
telling you that I won't let this work before you take a risk at your own
barrel and that risk is called typecasting explicitly typecasting it and
then you do that and then you get the truncated value but you took the
risk right you said that I want this to be worked working but okay I'm all right
with the truncation right and then if you and this explicit typecasting
right now we converted a value of a double into a shot and that means if you do
something like this that is you go this way right that is up or down side up
and this is for example when you want to convert a variable of a type double into
an end a float into a long along into a bite this is called we're trying to do
narrowing all right and for narrowing we always need an explicit typecast but
if you want to go or if you want to come in reverse right like this that is you
want to convert a variable of a type bite into an end or an end into a float or a
double that is what we call as appropriately as widening or even you can call it
broadening but I'll just stick to widening but for widening you don't need the
explicit typecast I'll say no typecast required right so whenever you're trying
to do widening there is not a typecast to be needed why because you're putting a
smaller value into a bigger container that would always fit in right and we'll
just have a look at exactly that now for example this is a shot and after this
you want this to be put in a s or a int I'll just say int value and you'll just
say s and see even without the typecast this worked and I'll say this is
because it was done with implicit type casting right where you don't need to put
in the cast but behind the scenes there's still a cast that is done for you
automatically by your new friends in the Java programming language right but
this just works and you just get a value as well I'll just say I'm sowed and
many value just run this quickly let's see we get a 72 so that is how explicit
typecasting works or implicit typecasting works again a rule of thumb
is whenever you're trying to do what I said as narrowing you always would
neither explicit typecast but whenever you do widening no typecast needed it
would be handled for you or to matically